Gary Paul Nabhan papers, 1969-
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Gary Paul Nabhan papers, 1969-
MS 337
Nabhan, Gary Paul
Papers, 1969-, of Gary Paul Nabhan, ethnobiologist, plant ecologist, and author. Contains journals and study notebooks dated from 1969 to 1997; his scholarly and popular published works; production materials relating to his works; and transparencies relating to animals, agriculture and landscapes in Southern Arizona and the Sonoran region.
6 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection. Request for permission to publish over 500 words from the collection must be obtained from Mr. Nabhan. Administration of copyright is retained by Mr. Nabhan.
Biographical Note
Gary Paul Nabhan was born on 17 March 1952 in Gary, Indiana, a son of Theodore B. and Wanda Mary (Goodwin) Nabhan.
He attended Cornell College in Mt. Vernon, Iowa; Prescott College in Prescott, Arizona, and received a PhD in Arid Lands Resources from the University of Arizona in 1983.
Nabhan has devoted his career to advocating the preservation of desert plants, native seeds, and the lifestyles of native desert people, including the Native American tribes of the southwestern United States. He has lived and worked with Native American tribes including the Tohono O'odham Indians during the time of gathering data for his doctoral dissertation, Papago Fields: Arid lands ethnobotany and agricultural ecology (University of Arizona, 1983).
He began his professional career as a research associate with the Office of Arid Land Studies at the University of Arizona. He was a co-founder in 1983 of Native Seeds/SEARCH, a grassroots conservation organization dedicated to collecting and preserving the native seeds of the desert southwest. He was assistant director at the Desert Botanical Garden in Phoenix, and later writer-in-residence and director of science at the Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum.
Nabhan is a member of the Scientific and Project Committee of The Ethnobiology and Conservation Team (ECT), an international group of biologists, activists, anthropologists, conservationists, philanthropists, entrepreneurs and artists committed to carrying out conservation at the grass roots level.
He is widely published in both scientific journals and the American trade press. Awards include a McArthur Fellowship, a Pew Scholarship for conservation research, and a John Burroughs Medal in 1987 for outstanding nature writing in Gathering the Desert.
Organization
This collection is organized into six series:
Series 1: Journals and notebooks,. 1969-1997
Series 2: Published materials, 1973 to 1997.
Series 3: Miscellaneous, 1980 to 1990
Series 4: Monographs, 1993 to 1997
Series 5: Production materials.
Series 6: Slides.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes Nabhan's archives of his fieldwork studies and written works. It includes personal journals, class notebooks, and fieldwork journals created during his educational and professional career. The published materials include most of the scholarly books and articles written or co-authored by Nabhan. The production materials demonstrate the research and collaboration in the scientific process, and relate to his work on Counting sheep: twenty ways of seeing desert bighorn and Why some like it hot: food, genes, and cultural diversity. The photographic materials are mostly transparencies of landscapes, agriculture, and animals in Southern Arizona and the Sonoran desert region.
Nabhan, Gary Paul -- Archives.; Native Seeds/Search (Organization); Biodiversity conservation -- West (U.S.); Desert plants -- Arizona.; Wild flowers -- Arizona.; Gastronomy.; Conservation biology -- West (U.S.); Pollinators -- West (U.S.); Endangered ecosystems.; Sonoran Desert.; Southwest, New -- Description and travel.; Southwest, New -- Environmental conditions.; Arizona -- Environmental conditions.; Natural history -- Arizona.; Seeds -- United States.; Plant conservation -- North America.; Ethnobotany -- Arizona.; Plant communities -- Sonoran desert.; Tohono O'odham Indians -- Ethnobotany.; 1975-1999
Container List
- Series 1: Journals and Notebooks, 1969-1997, Arrangement: Chronological
  Nature writing journals, notebooks, and fieldwork journals created by Nabhan and his associates, dated from 1969 to 1997. Descriptions of most of the individual items were supplied by Nabhan and appear in the inventory below. Correspondence or other papers found in the journals remain in the folder with the journal in which they were found. Some journals were placed in phase boxes.
  - Fieldwork Journal. 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Topics: Poetry, drawings. Places: Cornell College, Mt. Vernon, Iowa; Gary and Hobart, Indiana; 1st Earth Day Headquarters, Washington DC; Prescott College, Arizona.
  - Fieldwork Journal. 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Topics: Concrete poetry, "Multimedia Art." Place: Cornell College, Mt. Vernon, Iowa. Note: "First 1 1/2 yrs of undergraduate study"
  - Notebook. 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Topic: "Shamanism & the Beginnings of Art" Study Book. Place: Prescott College, Arizona.
  - Notebook. 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Topic: "Literature of the Deserts" Study Book. Place: Prescott College, Arizona. Gary Nabhan and Howard Lyon. Note: "Nabhan's First Sonoran Desert Writing"
  - Notebook. 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Topic: "Literature of Prairie & Plains" field course. Place: Prescott College. G. Nabhan, Howard Lyon, Cathy Preuss.
  - Nature Writing Journal. 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Topic: Spiritual reflections, Songs, poems. Romance with Karen Reichardt. Places: Tucson, Arizona; Rosemont, Arizona.
  - Field Journal. 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Topic: Pima and Papago ethnobotany fieldnotes and readings. Places: St. Johns / Komatke, Arizona; Laveen Little Tucson / Ali Cukson, Arizona; Fresnal Village / Jizwuli Dak, Arizona; Ventana Cave / Nakajigul, Arizona.
  - Field Plantings. 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Topic: Landscape and native crop plantings, Pre-Native Seeds/SEARCH garden trials. Places: 510 West Pelaar, Tucson, Arizona. Note on book: Garden Logbook and Experiment Record.
  - Field Journal. 1979-ca.1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Topic: Tohono O'odham agricultural fields-- and related interviews. Places: Ali Cukson / Little Tucson, Arizona; Ge Oidag / Big Fields, Arizona; Topawa, Arizona.
  - Field "Plantings" / Weed communities. 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Topic: Disturbance-responses of annuals on Hohokam terraces. Places: Tucson and Tortolita mountains; Marana, Arizona. Note: "Work with Karen Reichardt and Suzanne Fish" (some loose pages in book).
  - Nature Writing Journal. 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Topic: Papago (O'odham) Agricultural Terms from various dictionaries and ethnographies in preparation for PhD dissertation & The Desert Smells Like Rain.
  - Fieldwork Journal, Gary Nabhan & Karen Reichardt. 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Topic: Laura Kerman Oral History, Phenology of house w[est] of Tumamoc Hill. Places: Topawa & Tucson, Arizona; Cabeza Prieta, Arizona; (some loose pages in journal).
  - Fieldwork Journal. 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Topic: Sonoran Desert Ethnobotany, preludes to Gathering the Desert, Bacanora, Chiltepin, Palm; Gourds. Places: Eastern Sonora; Papagueriz Mexicali Valley, BCN; Tumacacori, Arizona; Magdalena, Sonora; Onavas, Sonora.
  - Fieldwork Journal. 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Topic Cucurbit (gourd) & bean ethnobotany & biogeography, Cactus population ecology. Places: Durango-Mazatlan hwy, Mexico; Creel, Chihuahua, Mexico; Eastern Sonora, Mexico; Western Tamaulipas, Mexico; Big Bend, Texas; Carlsbad, New Mexico.
  - Nature Writing Journal. 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Topic: Counting sheep, Biophilia, Geography of Childhood, O'odham concepts of wildness. Places: Tontozona, Arizona (ASU-sponsored workshop); Woodshole, Mass. (Yale-Harvard Biophilia Workshop); Gallup, NM (1st meeting of Traditional Native American Farmers Assoc.); Organpipe Cactus National Monument; Tohono O'odham Reservation.
  - Fieldnotes and Research. Summer 1997 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Topic: Boojums and Sonorisnos.
- Series 2: Published materials, 1973-1998, Arrangement: Chronological with folders numbered according to bibliography of Dr. Nabhan.
  Note: All authors are listed for co-authored works. All others are by Nabhan alone.
  Note: This collection contains numerous empty manila folders with bibliographic information but no actual publication. The empty folders are represented in this guide by gaps in the folder number sequence.
  - A characterization of Galapagos mangrove communities (with a preliminary consideration of their ecological succession in relation to coastal geomorphological evolution). Charles Darwin Research Institute, San Diego. 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The ecology of Laguna de la Cruz, Bahia de Kino, Sonora, Mexico: A preliminary manuscript done for Prescott College Center for Man & Environment from fieldwork in 1972 and 1973. Prescott College Center for Environment, Prescott. 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - A characterization of Galapagos mangrove communities (with a preliminary consideration of their ecological succession in relation to coastal geomorphological evolution). Charles Darwin Research Institute, San Diego. 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The ecology of Laguna de la Cruz, Bahia de Kino, Sonora, Mexico: A preliminary manuscript done for Prescott College Center for Man & Environment from fieldwork in 1972 and 1973. Prescott College Center for Environment, Prescott. 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 'Prairie revival': bringing native grasses back to pastures, backyards. High Country News, 6(22), 6-7. 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Felger, Richard S. and G. P. Nabhan. Agroecosystem diversity: a model from the Sonoran Desert. In AAAS Selected Symposium, 10: Social and Technological Management in Dry Lands: Past and Present, Indigenous and Imposed. Nancie L. Gonzalez, ed. Westview Press. (reprint copy and book). 1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Chiltepines! wild spice of the American southwest. El Palacio: Quarterly Journal of the Museum of New Mexico, 84(2), 30-34. 1978 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cottonwoods: sacred and sensible. High Country News, 10, 8-9. 1978, November 3 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Sheridan, Thomas Edward, and Gary Paul Nabhan. Living with a river: traditional farmers of the Rio San Miguel. The Journal of Arizona History 19, 1-16. 1978 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Nabhan, Gary P. and Richard S. Felger. Teparies in southwestern North America: a biogeographical and ethnohistorical study of Phaseolus acutifolius. Economic Botany 32(1), 2-19. 1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Tepary bean domestication: ecological and nutritional changes during Phaseolus acutifolius evolution. MS Thesis, University of Arizona. [Thesis is in UA Special Collections, E9791 1978 142. Folder contains a Nabhan article based on his thesis, Tepary Beans: The effects of domestication on adaptations to arid environments. Arid Lands Newsletter, 10(April 1979):11-16.] 1979 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Developing new crops is old idea in Arizona. Progressive Agriculture in Arizona. 30(3), 12-15. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - The ecology of floodwater farming in arid southwestern North America. Agro-Ecosystems, 5, 245-255. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Nabhan, G.P., C.W. Weber, and J.W. Berry. Legumes in the Papago- Pima Indian diet and ecological niche. The Kiva, 44(2-3), 173-190. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - New crops for desert farming. The New Farm, 1, 52-60. 1979, March-April (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Qui protege les semences qui nous sauveront? Mazingira 9, 53-58. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Nabhan, Gary, and David Yetman. Seeds: green revolution reaps cruel harvest. The Arizona Daily Star, July 15, 1979, H1. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Tepary beans: the effects of domestication on adaptations to arid environments. Arid Lands Newsletter 10, 11-16. 1979, April (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Southwestern Indian sunflowers. Desert Plants, 1(1), 23-26. 1979, August (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Who is saving the seeds to save us? Mazingira 9, 55-59. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Ammabroma sonorae, an endangered parasitic plant in extremely arid North America. Desert Plants, 2(3), 188-196. 1980 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Arid land agriculture: Native crops of the greater southwest. Dry Country News, 5, 10-12. 1980, Spring (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Arid land agriculture. Dry Country News, 6, 28-29. 1980, Summer (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Cottonwoods: sacred and sensible. Dry Country News 6, 52. 1980, Summer (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Nabhan, Gary, James Berry, Cynthia Anson, and Charles Weber. Papago Indian floodwater fields and tepary bean protein yields. Ecology of Food and Nutrition, 10, 71-78. 1980 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Hitt, Sam, and Gary Nabhan. Pitcher irrigation for dry soil gardens. Organic Gardening, 27, 124-127. 1980, November (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Raising hell... as well as wheat: Papago Indians burying the borderline. La Confluencia, a Magazine for the Southwest, 3(3&4), 18-22. 1980, Summer (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - The seeds of prehistory. Garden, 4, 8-12. 1980, May/June (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Nabhan, G.P., J.W. Berry, and C.W. Weber. Wild beans of the greater southwest: Phaseolus metcalfei and Phaseolus ritensis. Economic Botany 34(1), 68-85. 1980 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Nabhan, Gary, Alfred Whiting, Henry Dobyns, Richard Hevly, and Robert Euler. Devil's claw domestication: evidence from Southwestern Indian fields. Journal of Ethnobiology, 1(1), 135-164. 1981 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Berry, J., P.K. Bretting, G.P. Nabhan, and C. Weber. Domesticated Proboscidea parviflora: a potential oilseed crop for arid lands. Journal of Arid Environments 4, 147-160. 1981 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Nabhan, Gary, Cynthia Anson, Mahina Drees, and Danny Lopez. Kaicka: Seed saving the Papago-Pima Way: A guide for desert gardeners and farmers. Tucson, AZ: Meals for Millions/Freedom From Hunger Foundations. 1981 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Runoff farming for dry lands. The New Farm, 3, 50-53. 1981, May-June (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Niethammer, Carolyn, Gary Nabhan, Mahina Drees, and Cynthia Anson. Seed banks serving people: Highlights of a workshop, October 9-10, 1981. Tucson, AZ: Meals for Millions/Freedom From Hunger Foundation. 1981 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - The Sonoran Desert bioregion. Co-Evolution Quarterly, 32, 86 -87. (Also in this issue is a book review by Nabhan on Pueblo Indian Cookbook and Hopi Cookery, 51) 1981, Winter (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Nabhan, Gary, Ken Vogler, and Karen Reichhardt. Tepary bean crop ecology, Papago Indian Reservation, Arizona. Annual Report of the Bean Improvement Cooperative. 1981 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - The desert smells like rain: A naturalist in Papago Indian country. San Francisco: North Point Press. 1982 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - The desert smells like rain. Japanese edition. Translation rights arranged with Farrar, Straus & Giroux, Inc., New York through Tuttle - Mori Agency Inc., Tokyo. 1982 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Papago Indian desert agriculture and water control, 1697-1934. In Application of remote sensing in evaluating floodwater farming on the Papago Indian Reservation. Tucson: Applied Remote Sensing Program, Office of Arid Lands Studies, University of Arizona; Completion Report, OWRT Project No. C-90258-G. 1982 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Nabhan, Gary P., Amadeo M. Rea, Karen L. Reichhardt, Eric Mellink, and Charles F. Hutchinson. Papago influences on habitat and biotic diversity: Quitovac oasis ethnoecology. Journal of Ethnobiology 2(2), 124-143. 1982 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Sunflower of Indians of the Southwest. The Sunflower 8, 30 and 32. 1982, January (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Hopi protection of Helianthus anomalus, a rare sunflower. Southwestern Naturalist, 28(2), 231-235. 1983 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Kokopelli: The humpbacked flute player; a Native American patron saint for conserving agricultural diversity as a community responsibility. CoEvolution Quarterly, 37, 4-11. 1983, Spring (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Kokopelli: The humpbacked flute player. Reprinted in Ten Years of CoEvolution Quarterly: News that stayed news, 1947-57. San Francisco: North Point Press. 1983 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Papago fields: Arid lands ethnobotany and agricultural ecology. PhD dissertation, University of Arizona, Tucson. (UMI abstract is in folder. Copy is in UA Special Collections, E9791 1983 424). 1983 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Rea, Amadeo M., Gary P. Nabhan, and Karen L. Reichhardt. Sonoran desert oases: plants, birds, and native people. Environment Southwest, 503, 5-9. 1983, Autumn (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Nabhan, Gary Paul, and Helga Teiwes. Tepary beans, O’odham farmers and desert fields. Desert Plants 5(1), 15-37. (This issue was titled: The desert tepary as a food source: a journal symposium, edited by Gary Paul Nabhan. He wrote guest editorial inside front cover.) 1983 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Wild species protected by Arizona Hopi farmers. The Sunflower 9, 34-35. 1983, December (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Evidence of gene flow between cultivated Cucurbita mixta and a field edge population of wild Cucurbita at Onavas, Sonora. Cucurbit Genetics Cooperative Newsletter 7, 76-77. 1984 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Merrick, Laura C., and Gary P. Nabhan. Natural hybridization of wild Cucurbita sororia group and domesticated C. mixta in southern Sonora, Mexico. Cucurbit Genetics Cooperative Newsletter 7, 73-75. 1984 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Nabhan, Gary, and J. M. J. de Wet. Panicum sonorum in Sonoran Desert agriculture. Economic Botany, 38(1), 65-82. 1984 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Replenishing desert agriculture with native plants and their symbionts. In Meeting the expectations of the land: Essays in sustainable agriculture and stewardship. W. Jackson, W. Berry, and B. Colman, eds. San Francisco: North Point Press. 1984 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Gathering the desert. Tucson: University of Arizona Press. Winner of the John Burroughs Medal. File contains paperback from fourth printing. 1985-1990 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Nabhan, G.P. and B.T. Burns. Palmilla (Nolina) fiber: a native plant industry in arid and semi-arid U.S./Mexico borderlands. Journal of Arid Environments 9, 97-103. 1985 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Nabhan, Gary P., and Richard S. Felger. Wild desert relatives of crops: Their direct uses as food. In Plants for arid lands: Proceedings of the Kew International Conference on Economic Plants for Arid Lands held in the Jodrell Laboratory, Botanical Gardens, Kew, England, 23-27 July 1984. G.E. Wilkins, J.R. Goodin, D.V. Field, eds. London: Allen & Unwin, 19-33. 1985 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Nabhan, Gary P., and W. Bruce Masse. Floodwater agriculture in the Sonoran: Ethnographic and archaeological perspectives. Paper prepared for the 51st Annual Meeting of the Society for American Archaeology, 23-26 April. New Orleans. 1986 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - The garden’s goal: Reversing desert degradation. Agave 2, 14-15. 1986 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Regional seedstocks and Oscar Will’s vegetables: Learning from agricultural history. Seed Savers Exchange, Harvest ed, 178-180. 1986 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - The Sonoran Desert. In Arizona: The land and the people. T. Miller, ed. Tucson: University of Arizona Press. 1986 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Nabhan, Gary, Victor Gass, and Patrick Quirk. Thornberg’s fishhook cactus: Conserving a declining species. Agave 2, 4-8. 1986 (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Nabhan, G.P., J. Muruaga Matinez, F. Cardenas-Ramos, and B.T. Burns. Wild bean exploration in the Northwest Mexico and Southwest USA. FAO/IBPGR Plant Genetic Resources Newsletter 65, 23-25. 1986 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - The desert’s future. Agave: Quarterly Magazine of the Desert Botanical Garden, 2:10-13. 1987, Fall (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Ethnobiology and conservation: valuing diversity. Environment Southwest, 519, 28-31. 1987, Autumn (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Bretting, P.K., and G.P. Nabhan. Ethnobotany of devil’s claw (Proboscides parviflora ssp. parviflora: Martyniaceae) in the greater Southwest. Journal of California and Great Basin Anthropology, 8(2), 226-237. 1986 (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - Native foods of desert peoples found to control diabetes. The Seedhead News 19, 1,3. 1987 (Box 3, Folder 121)
  - Nurse plant ecology of threatened desert plants. In Rare & Endangered plants: A California symposium proceedings. T. Elias. Sacramento: California Native Plant Society. (Conference program and abstracts in folder; book missing.). 1987 (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - Plant domestication and folk-biological change: the Upper Piman/devil’s claw example. American Anthropologist, 89(1), 57-73. 1987 (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Saving native plants. American Land Forum, 12-14. 1987 (Box 3, Folder 125)
  - Using natural desert ecosystems as models for Agroforestry: The gray, spiney revolution. Paper presented at the Symposium on Strategies for Classification and Management of Native Vegetation for Food Production in Arid Zones, 12-16 October. Tucson, Arizona. 232-234, 250. 1987 (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - Pratt, R.D., and G.P. Nabhan. Evolution and diversity of Phaseolus acutifolius tepary genetic resources. In Genetic Resources of Phaseolus Beans. Paul Gepts, ed. Dordrecht: Kluwer Academic Publishers, 409-440. 1988 (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - Invisible erosion: the rise and fall of native farming. Journal of the Southwest 30, 550-572. 1988 (Box 3, Folder 130)
  - Southwest project cuts across cultural, national boundaries. Center for Plant Conservation, 3(2), 1 and 8. 1988 (Box 3, Folder 131)
  - Andres, Thomas C., and Gary P. Nabhan. Taxonomic rank and rarity of Cucurbita okeechobeensis. Rep-Cucurbit-Genet-Coop, 11, 83-85. 1988 (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - Nabhan, Gary Paul, Robert Tobichaux, Mark Slater, and Suzanne Nelson. Useful desert plants for low-input polycultures. Arid Lands Newsletter, 27, 11-14. 1988 (Box 3, Folder 134)
  - Enduring seeds: Native American agriculture and wild plant conservation. San Francisco: North Point Press. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 135)
  - Nabhan, Gary Paul, and Ann Zwinger. Field notes and the literary process. In Writing Natural History: Dialogues with Authors. Edward Lueders, ed. Salt Lake City: University of Utah Press. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 137)
  - Gift of the Manitok: from the waters of northern Wisconsin, the Ojibway reap nature's blessing--wild rice. Harrowsmith, 4, 72-79. 1989, February (Box 3, Folder 140)
  - Nabhan, Gary Paul, Wendy Hodgson, and Frances Fellows. A meager living on lava and sand? Hia Ced O'odham food resources and habitat diversity in oral and documentary histories. Journal of the Southwest 31(4), 508-533. Two copies. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - Nabhan, Gary, and David Valenciano. A modest proposal: Restoring the Sonoran Desert at Barnes Butte Bajada. Agave 3, 3-5. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 142)
  - On the bright edges of the world: southwest traditions of knowing and growing herbs. The Herb Companion, 1, 12-14. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 143)
  - Plants at risk in the Sonoran Desert: An international concern. Agave 3(3), 14-15. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 144)
  - Hodgson, Wendy, Gary Nabhan, and Liz Ecker. Prehistoric fields in Central Arizona: Conserving rediscovered agave cultivans. Agave 3, 9-11. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 147)
  - Rescuing Arizona's endangered plants. Arizona Highways, 65(3), 34-41. 1989, March (Box 3, Folder 148)
  - Seeds of renewal. World Monitor 2(1), 17-20. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 149)
  - Andres, Thomas C., and Gary P. Nabhan. Taxonomic rank and rarity of Cucurbita okeechobeensis. FAO/IPBGR Plant Genetic Resources Newsletter, 75/76, 21-22. 1988 (Box 3, Folder 150)
  - A child's sense of wilderness. Orion, 9, 54-57. 1990 (Box 3, Folder 151)
  - Conservationists and forest service join forces to wave wild chiles. Diversity 6(3&4), 47-48. 1990 (Box 3, Folder 152)